Newton’s Laws of Motion 
Purpose 
This lab experiementally examines the relationships between unbalanced forces, 
mass, and acceleration. 
Description 
We used an air track, two gliders, five washers, a length of string, a post-it note, 
and two photogates. The glider is placed on the track, a string with one washer 
is attached to the car the string goes over a pulley to allow the washer to hang. 
The other washers were placed on the glider. Finally the post-it note is placed 
on one of the gliders like a flag to activate the photogates. 
Using the photogates we measured the time between the two photogates 
while the glider accelerated by being pulled by the washer. Then, we added the 
other glider in front of the other car and again measured the acceleration time. 
Another washer is added to the string and the previous steps are repeated until 
after all five washers are hanging from the string. 
Then the whole experiment is repeated the same way as before except the 
velocity is now being measured. A photogate after the point on the track where 
the gliders stop accelerating. 

Results 
The slopes of the lines on the graph created by our data indicate the masses of 
the system because the graph is more or less a graph of m = F 
a . For the red 
car only the equation of the line is F = .0598a + .0055 so experimentally the 
mass of the system is .0598 kg. The theoretical mass is .0599 kg, and the error 
in this case is .17%. For the red and blue car together the experimental mass of 
the system is .1087 kg, and the theoretical mass is .1057 kg. The error is 2.8% 
with the red and blue car.

Conclusion 
The masses of the systems were found experimentally to be .0599 kg and .1057 
kg. Although there was errors of .17% and 2.8%, this experiment plainly shows 
the close relationship of force, mass, and acceleration as Newton envisioned it— 
F = ma. The results, I believe, are acceptable, especially with the data on the 
red car only.

Forces Along an Incline 
Purpose 
This lab examines friction on an incline of varying angles. Mechanical advantage 
and efficiency will also be analyzed. 
Description 
This lab uses a board that can be inclined at different angles, the upper end 
of the board is fixed with a pulley. Also, a wood block with four rubber feet 
affixed to one side is used. A string is attached to the block and strung over the 
pulley with masses attached to the end. 
First, the block is placed on the board without any masses attached to it the 
board is inclined until the block moves down the incline at a constant speed. 
This is done on the side with rubber feet and on a side without. From this we 
can determine the coefficient of kinetic friction. 
Next, masses are attached to the end of string until the block travels up the 
board at a constant speed. This is done at 10◦ increments from 0◦ to 70◦ . Once 
again both sides of the block are measured. 

The angle at which fk equals the force down the incline on rubber is 21◦ , on 
wood it is 17.5◦ . 
The mass of the block is 139.4 g.

Conclusion 
The measured masses tended to be relatively close to the predicted masses, esqe- 
cially given the masses are in 10 gram increments. The predicted and measured 
masses started to converge as the mass needed increased. 
The ideal and the actual mechanical advantage converge as the angle in- 
creases. As the angle increases the normal force decreases which means the 
friction also decreases demonstrated by the graph. 
Like with before, the greater the angle the board is inclined the greater 
efficiency is obtained. Besides the friction, the only other thing that may have 
a non-negligible adverse effect on the efficiency is any friction created by the 
pulley.

Launching a Ball 
Purpose 
Determine the relationship between the release speed of a ball and the elevation 
of its initial position on an inclined plane. 
Description 
An inclined plane is attached to the top of a counter, a metal ball is rolled down 
the plane and hits a piece of carbon paper. The distance from where the ball 
left the inclined plane to where the ball hits the ground is measured on the 
ground. This is repeated several times by rolling the ball at different heights on 
the inclined plane. 

Conclusion 
When applying the function v0 = 22.387h.675 to the original graph it actually 
does not fit the curve very well at all. I attribute this to my eyeballing of the 
best fit line for log v vs. log h and my somewhat inaccurate measuring of its 
slope and y-intercept.

Standing Waves 
Richard Johnson 
Introduction 
Standing waves occur on strings at discrete frenquencies. This lab examines those frequencies which standing 
waves occur and the number of segments that are produced. 
Procedure 
Equipment Used: 
• A string 
• An electric vibrator 
• A signal generator 
• A mountable pulley 
• A set of masses 
Attach the pulley to the edge of table and secure the vibrator on the table about four feet away from 
the pulley. Plug the signal generator into the vibrator. Attach one end of the string to the vibrator, string 
it over the pulley and to that end attach 600 grams. 
Turn on the signal generator with a frequency less than 1 Hz, and the amplitude at about 3/4 power. 
Increase the frequency slowly until the string’s fundamental mode is seen, where n = 1. Now record the the 
frequency, wavelength, and the wave number. Continue to record information for up to n = 6. 

Conclusion 
The wave speed was calculated theoretically to be 16.0944 m/s which was corroborated relatively well by 
the experimental values of v. The average percent error was 4.4477%, the greatest error occured at n = 5: 
5.8381%, and the smallest error occured at n = 3: 2.2064%. Interestingly the first node’s error was the third 
smallest despite the fact that it should have been the hardest to find. Although the errors aren’t as small as 
it would be preferable they aren’t too terribly bad either. 

EM Wave Diffraction 
Richard Johnson 
Introduction 
This lab examines the results of the diffraction of electromagnetic waves, specifically microwaves. Also 
Thomas Young’s double-slit experiment will be recreated and examined to determine the wavelength of the 
EM waves being produced. 
Procedure 
Equipment Used: 
• A microwave generator and a receiver with a power meter. 
• A rail system allowing the generator and receiver to sit on the rails and between them a place to insert 
different barriers. The rail the receiver sits on must be able to orbit around the center with the barrier. 
• A metal plate with two slits. 
• A metal plate with one slit. 
• A small metal barrier with no slits. 
Set the generator and receiver opposite of each other with no barrier between them. Turn on the generator. 
Change the power setting on the generator and the gain setting on the receiver until the receiver reads a 
power of 80%; for the small barrier with no slits the power setting should be less than 80%. 
Set the double-slit plate into the center and record the resulting power when the generator and receiver 
are opposite each other 0◦ . Move the receiver 5◦ from the previous setting and record the power once again, 
repeat this until the receiver is at 80◦ . Then repeat with the two other barriers. 
With the one slit and the two slit the power readings going the other direction from 0◦ should be the 
same. The slit-less barrier, however, should be placed off to one side of the center, and readings should be 
taken from 0◦ to 80◦ in both directions. 

According to the data the first constructive interference pattern from the maximum interference pattern 
of the double slit experiment is at 25◦ . So the wavelength of the microwaves can be calculated by λ = d sin(Θ) 
where d is the distance between the center of the slits (.073m). 

Conclusion 
Using the data gathered from double slit experiment the wavelength of the EM waves being produced is 3.08 
cm. The error of the results were .6%. The error is remarkably small and most likely well within the range 
of acceptable errors. 

Converging and Diverging Lenses 
Richard Johnson 
Data 
Lens 3 and 4 are converging lenses and lens 5 is a diverging lens. The focal length estimate of lens 3 is 5 cm 
and the estimate of lens 4 is 19 cm. 

Using the line fits on graph 2 we can get the focal lengths of the lenses. By choosing a point on the line, 
adding the point’s components and taking the inverse we get the focal length. The y-intercepts are good 
candidates for points. 

Michelson-Morley Interferometer 
Richard Johnson 
Introduction 
This lab recreates the Michelson-Morely Interferometer experiment using microwaves in place of light. 
Procedure 
Arrange the four arms of the interferometer perpendicular to each other. Put the two full mirrors adjacent 
to each at the 25 cm mark. Place the receiver at the 10 cm mark on the third arm. The microwave generator 
should be placed near the end of the fourth arm. Place the double slit “half mirror” in the center angled 
45◦ away from the generator and towards the receiver. 
Now calibrate the generator and receiver so the receiver reads a decent amount of power at maximum 
constructive interference. 
Slowly move the mirror that is opposite of the receiver from 30 cm to around 23 cm. Record the power 
reading at 1 mm increments. 

While recording the data the screw that pushed the mirror caused the mirror to tilt forward. This was 
fixed; however, it caused a bit of a “hiccup” in the data starting at about 27 cm. 
The distance between the peaks of power can be used to calculate the wavelength of the microwaves using 
the formula = 2 
∆: 
  
  
Conclusion 
The frequency of the microwaves were calculated from the data gathered to be 10 GHz while the given 
frequency was 9.83 GHz. The error was only 1.73%, which seems very reasonable given how many digits 
the distances were measured to. Interestingly the “hiccup” had less effect on the result than I would have 
suspected. 
